2 Using the Tutorial Examples

This chapter tells you everything you need to know to install, build, and run the examples.

The following topics are addressed here:

Required Software

Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server

Starting the Administration Console

Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server

Building the Examples

Tutorial Example Directory Structure

Java EE 7 Maven Archetypes in the Tutorial

Getting the Latest Updates to the Tutorial

Debugging Java EE Applications

2.1 Required Software

The following software is required to run the examples:

Java Platform, Standard Edition

Java EE 7 Software Development Kit

Java EE 7 Tutorial Component

NetBeans IDE

Apache Maven

2.1.1 Java Platform, Standard Edition

To build, deploy, and run the examples, you need a copy of the Java Platform, Standard Edition Development Kit (JDK). You must use JDK 7 Update 65 or above or JDK 8 Update 20 or above. You can download JDK software from http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html.

2.1.2 Java EE 7 Software Development Kit

GlassFish Server Open Source Edition 4.1 is targeted as the build and runtime environment for the tutorial examples. To build, deploy, and run the examples, you need a copy of GlassFish Server and, optionally, NetBeans IDE. To obtain GlassFish Server, you must install the Java EE 7 Software Development Kit (SDK) Update 1, which you can download from http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaee/downloads/index.html. Make sure that you download the Java EE 7 SDK Update 1, not the Java EE 7 Web Profile SDK Update 1.

2.1.2.1 SDK Installation Tips

The Java EE 7 SDK Update 1 is installed from a ZIP file. It sets the default administration user name as admin with no required password. The Admin Port is set to 4848, and the HTTP Port is set to 8080.

This tutorial refers to as-install-parent, the directory where you install GlassFish Server. For example, the default installation directory on Microsoft Windows is C:\glassfish4, so as-install-parent is C:\glassfish4. GlassFish Server itself is installed in as-install, the glassfish directory under as-install-parent. So on Microsoft Windows, as-install is C:\glassfish4\glassfish.

After you install GlassFish Server, add the following directories to your PATH to avoid having to specify the full path when you use commands:

as-install-parent/bin
as-install/bin

2.1.3 Java EE 7 Tutorial Component

The tutorial component, including the documentation and example source, is contained in the Java EE 7 SDK Update 1.

Updates to the Java EE 7 Tutorial are published periodically. For details on obtaining these updates, see Getting the Latest Updates to the Tutorial.

2.1.4 NetBeans IDE

The NetBeans integrated development environment (IDE) is a free, open-source IDE for developing Java applications, including enterprise applications. NetBeans IDE supports the Java EE platform. You can build, package, deploy, and run the tutorial examples from within NetBeans IDE.

To run the tutorial examples, you need the latest version of NetBeans IDE. You can download NetBeans IDE from https://www.netbeans.org/downloads/index.html. Make sure that you download the Java EE bundle.

2.1.4.1 To Install NetBeans IDE without GlassFish Server

When you install NetBeans IDE, do not install the version of GlassFish Server that comes with NetBeans IDE. To skip the installation of GlassFish Server, follow these steps.

On the first page of the NetBeans IDE Installer wizard, deselect the check box for GlassFish Server and click OK.

Accept both the License Agreement and the Junit License Agreement.

A few of the tutorial examples use the Junit library, so you should install it.

Continue with the installation of NetBeans IDE.

2.1.4.2 To Add GlassFish Server as a Server Using NetBeans IDE

To run the tutorial examples in NetBeans IDE, you must add your GlassFish Server as a server in NetBeans IDE. Follow these instructions to add GlassFish Server to NetBeans IDE.

From the Tools menu, choose Servers.

In the Servers wizard, click Add Server.

Under Choose Server, select GlassFish Server and click Next.

Under Server Location, browse to the location of the Java EE 7 SDK and click Next.

Under Domain Location, select Register Local Domain.

Click Finish.

2.1.5 Apache Maven

Maven is a Java technology–based build tool developed by the Apache Software Foundation and is used to build, package, and deploy the tutorial examples. To run the tutorial examples from the command line, you need Maven 3.0 or higher. If you do not already have Maven, you can install it from:

http://maven.apache.org

Be sure to add the maven-install/bin directory to your path.

If you are using NetBeans IDE to build and run the examples, it includes a copy of Maven.

2.2 Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server

You can start and stop GlassFish Server using either NetBeans IDE or the command line.

2.2.1 To Start GlassFish Server Using NetBeans IDE

Click the Services tab.

Expand Servers.

Right-click the GlassFish Server instance and select Start.

2.2.2 To Stop GlassFish Server Using NetBeans IDE

To stop GlassFish Server using NetBeans IDE, right-click the GlassFish Server instance and select Stop.

2.2.3 To Start GlassFish Server Using the Command Line

To start GlassFish Server from the command line, open a terminal window or command prompt and execute the following:

asadmin start-domain --verbose

A domain is a set of one or more GlassFish Server instances managed by one administration server. The following elements are associated with a domain:

The GlassFish Server port number: The default is 8080.

The administration server's port number: The default is 4848.

An administration user name and password: The default user name is admin, and by default no password is required.

You specify these values when you install GlassFish Server. The examples in this tutorial assume that you chose the default ports as well as the default user name and lack of password.

With no arguments, the start-domain command initiates the default domain, which is domain1. The --verbose flag causes all logging and debugging output to appear on the terminal window or command prompt. The output also goes into the server log, which is located in domain-dir/logs/server.log.

2.2.4 To Stop GlassFish Server Using the Command Line

To stop GlassFish Server, open a terminal window or command prompt and execute:

asadmin stop-domain domain1

2.3 Starting the Administration Console

To administer GlassFish Server and manage users, resources, and Java EE applications, use the Administration Console tool. GlassFish Server must be running before you invoke the Administration Console. To start the Administration Console, open a browser at http://localhost:4848/.

2.3.1 To Start the Administration Console Using NetBeans IDE

Click the Services tab.

Expand Servers.

Right-click the GlassFish Server instance and select View Domain Admin Console.

Note:

NetBeans IDE uses your default web browser to open the Administration Console.

2.4 Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server

GlassFish Server includes the Java DB database server.

To start the Java DB server from the command line, open a terminal window or command prompt and execute:

asadmin start-database

To stop the Java DB server from the command line, open a terminal window or command prompt and execute:

asadmin stop-database

For information about the Java DB included with GlassFish Server, see http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javadb/overview/index.html.

2.4.1 To Start the Database Server Using NetBeans IDE

When you start GlassFish Server using NetBeans IDE, the database server starts automatically. If you ever need to start the server manually, however, follow these steps.

Click the Services tab.

Expand Databases.

Right-click Java DB and select Start Server.

Next Steps

To stop the database using NetBeans IDE, right-click Java DB and select Stop Server.

2.5 Building the Examples

The tutorial examples are distributed with a configuration file for either NetBeans IDE or Maven. Either NetBeans IDE or Maven may be used to build, package, deploy, and run the examples. Directions for building the examples are provided in each chapter.

2.6 Tutorial Example Directory Structure

To facilitate iterative development and keep application source files separate from compiled files, the tutorial examples use the Maven application directory structure.

Each application module has the following structure:

pom.xml: Maven build file

src/main/java: Java source files for the module

src/main/resources: configuration files for the module, with the exception of web applications

src/main/webapp: web pages, style sheets, tag files, and images (web applications only)

src/main/webapp/WEB-INF: configuration files for web applications (web applications only)

When an example has multiple application modules packaged into an EAR file, its submodule directories use the following naming conventions:

example-name-app-client: application clients

example-name-ejb: enterprise bean JAR files

example-name-war: web applications

example-name-ear: enterprise applications

example-name-common: library JAR containing components, classes, and files used by other modules

The Maven build files (pom.xml) distributed with the examples contain goals to compile and assemble the application into the target directory and deploy the archive to GlassFish Server.

2.7 Java EE 7 Maven Archetypes in the Tutorial

Some of the chapters have instructions on how to build an example application using Maven archetypes. Archetypes are templates for generating a particular Maven project. The Tutorial includes several Maven archetypes for generating Java EE 7 projects.

2.7.1 Installing the Tutorial Archetypes

You must install the included Maven archetypes into your local Maven repository before you can create new projects based on the archetypes. You can install the archetypes using NetBeans IDE or Maven.

2.7.1.1 Installing the Tutorial Archetypes Using NetBeans IDE

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples

Select the archetypes folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the archetypes project and select Build.

2.7.1.2 Installing the Tutorial Archetypes Using Maven

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/archetypes/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

2.8 Getting the Latest Updates to the Tutorial

Check for any updates to the tutorial by using the Update Tool included with the Java EE 7 SDK.

2.8.1 To Update the Tutorial Using NetBeans IDE

Open the Services tab in NetBeans IDE and expand Servers.

Right-click the GlassFish Server instance and select View Domain Update Center to display the Update Tool.

Select Available Updates in the tree to display a list of updated packages.

Look for updates to the Java EE 7 Tutorial (javaee-tutorial) package.

If there is an updated version of the Tutorial, select Java EE 7 Tutorial (javaee-tutorial) and click Install.

2.8.2 To Update the Tutorial Using the Command Line

Open a terminal window and enter the following command to display the Update Tool:

updatetool

Select Available Updates in the tree to display a list of updated packages.

Look for updates to the Java EE 7 Tutorial (javaee-tutorial) package.

If there is an updated version of the Tutorial, select Java EE 7 Tutorial (javaee-tutorial) and click Install.

2.9 Debugging Java EE Applications

This section explains how to determine what is causing an error in your application deployment or execution.

2.9.1 Using the Server Log

One way to debug applications is to look at the server log in domain-dir/logs/server.log. The log contains output from GlassFish Server and your applications. You can log messages from any Java class in your application with System.out.println and the Java Logging APIs (documented at http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/guides/logging/index.html) and from web components with the ServletContext.log method.

If you use NetBeans IDE, logging output appears in the Output window as well as the server log.

If you start GlassFish Server with the --verbose flag, all logging and debugging output will appear on the terminal window or command prompt and the server log. If you start GlassFish Server in the background, debugging information is available only in the log. You can view the server log with a text editor or with the Administration Console log viewer.

2.9.1.1 To Use the Administration Console Log Viewer

Select the GlassFish Server node.

Click View Log Files.

The log viewer opens and displays the last 40 entries.

To display other entries, follow these steps.

Click Modify Search.

Specify any constraints on the entries you want to see.

Click Search at the top of the log viewer.

2.9.2 Using a Debugger

GlassFish Server supports the Java Platform Debugger Architecture (JPDA). With JPDA, you can configure GlassFish Server to communicate debugging information using a socket.

2.9.2.1 To Debug an Application Using a Debugger

Follow these steps to enable debugging in GlassFish Server using the Administration Console:

Expand the Configurations node, then expand the server-config node.

Select the JVM Settings node. The default debug options are set to:

-agentlib:jdwp=transport=dt_socket,server=y,suspend=n,address=9009

As you can see, the default debugger socket port is 9009. You can change it to a port not in use by GlassFish Server or another service.

Select the Debug Enabled check box.

Click Save.

Stop GlassFish Server and then restart it.

6 Getting Started with Web Applications

This chapter introduces web applications, which typically use JavaServer Faces technology and/or Java Servlet technology. A web application is a dynamic extension of a web or application server. Web applications are of the following types:

Presentation-oriented: A presentation-oriented web application generates interactive web pages containing various types of markup language (HTML, XHTML, XML, and so on) and dynamic content in response to requests. Development of presentation-oriented web applications is covered in Chapter 7, "JavaServer Faces Technology," through Chapter 17, "Java Servlet Technology."

Service-oriented: A service-oriented web application implements the endpoint of a web service. Presentation-oriented applications are often clients of service-oriented web applications. Development of service-oriented web applications is covered in Chapter 28, "Building Web Services with JAX-WS," and Chapter 29, "Building RESTful Web Services with JAX-RS," in Part VI, "Web Services."

The following topics are addressed here:

Web Applications

Web Application Lifecycle

A Web Module That Uses JavaServer Faces Technology: The hello1 Example

A Web Module That Uses Java Servlet Technology: The hello2 Example

Configuring Web Applications

Further Information about Web Applications

6.1 Web Applications

In the Java EE platform, web components provide the dynamic extension capabilities for a web server. Web components can be Java servlets, web pages implemented with JavaServer Faces technology, web service endpoints, or JSP pages. Figure 6-1 illustrates the interaction between a web client and a web application that uses a servlet. The client sends an HTTP request to the web server. A web server that implements Java Servlet and JavaServer Pages technology converts the request into an HTTPServletRequest object. This object is delivered to a web component, which can interact with JavaBeans components or a database to generate dynamic content. The web component can then generate an HTTPServletResponse or can pass the request to another web component. A web component eventually generates a HTTPServletResponse object. The web server converts this object to an HTTP response and returns it to the client.

Figure 6-1 Java Web Application Request Handling

Description of "Figure 6-1 Java Web Application Request Handling"

Servlets are Java programming language classes that dynamically process requests and construct responses. Java technologies, such as JavaServer Faces and Facelets, are used for building interactive web applications. (Frameworks can also be used for this purpose.) Although servlets and JavaServer Faces and Facelets pages can be used to accomplish similar things, each has its own strengths. Servlets are best suited for service-oriented applications (web service endpoints can be implemented as servlets) and the control functions of a presentation-oriented application, such as dispatching requests and handling nontextual data. JavaServer Faces and Facelets pages are more appropriate for generating text-based markup, such as XHTML, and are generally used for presentation-oriented applications.

Web components are supported by the services of a runtime platform called a web container. A web container provides such services as request dispatching, security, concurrency, and lifecycle management. A web container also gives web components access to such APIs as naming, transactions, and email.

Certain aspects of web application behavior can be configured when the application is installed, or deployed, to the web container. The configuration information can be specified using Java EE annotations or can be maintained in a text file in XML format called a web application deployment descriptor (DD). A web application DD must conform to the schema described in the Java Servlet specification.

This chapter gives a brief overview of the activities involved in developing web applications. First, it summarizes the web application lifecycle and explains how to package and deploy very simple web applications on GlassFish Server. The chapter then moves on to configuring web applications and discusses how to specify the most commonly used configuration parameters.

6.2 Web Application Lifecycle

A web application consists of web components; static resource files, such as images and cascading style sheets (CSS); and helper classes and libraries. The web container provides many supporting services that enhance the capabilities of web components and make them easier to develop. However, because a web application must take these services into account, the process for creating and running a web application is different from that of traditional stand-alone Java classes.

The process for creating, deploying, and executing a web application can be summarized as follows:

Develop the web component code.

Develop the web application deployment descriptor, if necessary.

Compile the web application components and helper classes referenced by the components.

Optionally, package the application into a deployable unit.

Deploy the application into a web container.

Access a URL that references the web application.

Developing web component code is covered in the later chapters. Steps 2 through 4 are expanded on in the following sections and illustrated with a Hello, World–style, presentation-oriented application. This application allows a user to enter a name into an HTML form and then displays a greeting after the name is submitted.

The Hello application contains two web components that generate the greeting and the response. This chapter discusses the following simple applications:

hello1, a JavaServer Faces technology–based application that uses two XHTML pages and a managed bean

hello2, a servlet-based web application in which the components are implemented by two servlet classes

The applications are used to illustrate tasks involved in packaging, deploying, configuring, and running an application that contains web components.

6.3 A Web Module That Uses JavaServer Faces Technology: The hello1 Example

The hello1 application is a web module that uses JavaServer Faces technology to display a greeting and response. You can use a text editor to view the application files, or you can use NetBeans IDE.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/hello1/ directory.

6.3.1 To View the hello1 Web Module Using NetBeans IDE

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the hello1 folder and click Open Project.

Expand the Web Pages node and double-click the index.xhtml file to view it in the editor.

The index.xhtml file is the default landing page for a Facelets application. In a typical Facelets application, web pages are created in XHTML. For this application, the page uses simple tag markup to display a form with a graphic image, a header, a field, and two command buttons:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">
    <h:head>
        <title>Facelets Hello Greeting</title>
    </h:head>
    <h:body>
        <h:form>
            <h:graphicImage url="#{resource['images:duke.waving.gif']}"
                            alt="Duke waving his hand"/>
            <h2>Hello, my name is Duke. What's yours?</h2>
            <h:inputText id="username"
                         title="My name is: "
                         value="#{hello.name}"
                         required="true"
                         requiredMessage="Error: A name is required."
                         maxlength="25" />
            <p></p>
            <h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit" action="response">
            </h:commandButton>
            <h:commandButton id="reset" value="Reset" type="reset">
            </h:commandButton>
        </h:form>
        ...
    </h:body>
</html>

The most complex element on the page is the inputText field. The maxlength attribute specifies the maximum length of the field. The required attribute specifies that the field must be filled out; the requiredMessage attribute provides the error message to be displayed if the field is left empty. The title attribute provides the text to be used by screen readers for the visually disabled. Finally, the value attribute contains an expression that will be provided by the Hello managed bean.

The web page connects to the Hello managed bean through the Expression Language (EL) value expression #{hello.name}, which retrieves the value of the name property from the managed bean. Note the use of hello to reference the managed bean Hello. If no name is specified in the @Named annotation of the managed bean, the managed bean is always accessed with the first letter of the class name in lowercase.

The Submit commandButton element specifies the action as response, meaning that when the button is clicked, the response.xhtml page is displayed.

Double-click the response.xhtml file to view it.

The response page appears. Even simpler than the greeting page, the response page contains a graphic image, a header that displays the expression provided by the managed bean, and a single button whose action element transfers you back to the index.xhtml page:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">
    <h:head>
        <title>Facelets Hello Response</title>
    </h:head>
    <h:body>
        <h:form>
            <h:graphicImage url="#{resource['images:duke.waving.gif']}"
                            alt="Duke waving his hand"/>
            <h2>Hello, #{hello.name}!</h2>
            <p></p>
            <h:commandButton id="back" value="Back" action="index" />
        </h:form>
    </h:body>
</html>

Expand the Source Packages node, then the javaeetutorial.hello1 node.

Double-click the Hello.java file to view it.

The Hello class, called a managed bean class, provides getter and setter methods for the name property used in the Facelets page expressions. By default, the expression language refers to the class name, with the first letter in lowercase (hello.name).

package javaeetutorial.hello1;

import javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped;
import javax.inject.Named;

@Named
@RequestScoped
public class Hello {

    private String name;

    public Hello() {
    }

    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }

    public void setName(String user_name) {
        this.name = user_name;
    }
}

If you use the default name for the bean class, you can specify @Model as the annotation instead of having to specify both @Named and @RequestScoped. The @Model annotation is called a stereotype, a term for an annotation that encapsulates other annotations. It is described later in Using Stereotypes in CDI Applications. Some examples will use @Model where it is appropriate.

Under the Web Pages node, expand the WEB-INF node and double-click the web.xml file to view it.

The web.xml file contains several elements that are required for a Facelets application. All of the following are created automatically when you use NetBeans IDE to create an application.

A context parameter specifying the project stage:

    <context-param>
        <param-name>javax.faces.PROJECT_STAGE</param-name>
        <param-value>Development</param-value>
    </context-param>

A context parameter provides configuration information needed by a web application. An application can define its own context parameters. In addition, JavaServer Faces technology and Java Servlet technology define context parameters that an application can use.

A servlet element and its servlet-mapping element specifying the FacesServlet. All files with the .xhtml suffix will be matched:

    <servlet>
        <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
        <servlet-class>javax.faces.webapp.FacesServlet</servlet-class>
        <load-on-startup>1</load-on-startup>
    </servlet>
    <servlet-mapping>
        <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
        <url-pattern>*.xhtml</url-pattern>
    </servlet-mapping>

A welcome-file-list element specifying the location of the landing page:

    <welcome-file-list>
        <welcome-file>index.xhtml</welcome-file>
    </welcome-file-list>

6.3.1.1 Introduction to Scopes

In the Hello.java class, the annotations javax.inject.Named and javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped identify the class as a managed bean using request scope. Scope defines how application data persists and is shared.

The most commonly used scopes in JavaServer Faces applications are the following:

Request (@RequestScoped): Request scope persists during a single HTTP request in a web application. In an application like hello1, in which the application consists of a single request and response, the bean uses request scope.

Session (@SessionScoped): Session scope persists across multiple HTTP requests in a web application. When an application consists of multiple requests and responses where data needs to be maintained, beans use session scope.

Application (@ApplicationScoped): Application scope persists across all users' interactions with a web application.

For more information on scopes in JavaServer Faces technology, see Using Managed Bean Scopes.

6.3.2 Packaging and Deploying the hello1 Web Module

A web module must be packaged into a WAR in certain deployment scenarios and whenever you want to distribute the web module. You can package a web module into a WAR file by using Maven or by using the IDE tool of your choice. This tutorial shows you how to use NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, and deploy the hello1 sample application.

You can deploy a WAR file to GlassFish Server by:

Using NetBeans IDE

Using the asadmin command

Using the Administration Console

Copying the WAR file into the domain-dir/autodeploy/ directory

Throughout the tutorial, you will use NetBeans IDE or Maven for packaging and deploying.

6.3.2.1 To Build and Package the hello1 Web Module Using NetBeans IDE

Start GlassFish Server as described in To Start GlassFish Server Using NetBeans IDE, if you have not already done so.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the hello1 folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the hello1 project and select Build. This command deploys the project to the server.

6.3.2.2 To Build and Package the hello1 Web Module Using Maven

Start GlassFish Server as described in To Start GlassFish Server Using the Command Line, if you have not already done so.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/hello1/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command spawns any necessary compilations and creates the WAR file in tut-install/examples/web/jsf/hello1/target/. It then deploys the project to the server.

6.3.3 Viewing Deployed Web Modules

GlassFish Server provides two ways to view the deployed web modules: the Administration Console and the asadmin command. You can also use NetBeans IDE to view deployed modules.

6.3.3.1 To View Deployed Web Modules Using the Administration Console

Open the URL http://localhost:4848/ in a browser.

Select the Applications node.

The deployed web modules appear in the Deployed Applications table.

6.3.3.2 To View Deployed Web Modules Using the asadmin Command

Enter the following command:

asadmin list-applications

6.3.3.3 To View Deployed Web Modules Using NetBeans IDE

In the Services tab, expand the Servers node, then expand the GlassFish Server node.

Expand the Applications node to view the deployed modules.

6.3.4 Running the Deployed hello1 Web Module

Now that the web module is deployed, you can view it by opening the application in a web browser. By default, the application is deployed to host localhost on port 8080. The context root of the web application is hello1.

Open a web browser.

Enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/hello1/

In the field, enter your name and click Submit.

The response page displays the name you submitted. Click Back to try again.

6.3.4.1 Dynamic Reloading of Deployed Modules

If dynamic reloading is enabled, you do not have to redeploy an application or module when you change its code or deployment descriptors. All you have to do is copy the changed pages or class files into the deployment directory for the application or module. The deployment directory for a web module named context-root is domain-dir/applications/context-root. The server checks for changes periodically and redeploys the application, automatically and dynamically, with the changes.

This capability is useful in a development environment because it allows code changes to be tested quickly. Dynamic reloading is not recommended for a production environment, however, because it may degrade performance. In addition, whenever a reload takes place, the sessions at that time become invalid, and the client must restart the session.

In GlassFish Server, dynamic reloading is enabled by default.

6.3.5 Undeploying the hello1 Web Module

You can undeploy web modules and other types of enterprise applications by using either NetBeans IDE or Maven.

6.3.5.1 To Undeploy the hello1 Web Module Using NetBeans IDE

In the Services tab, expand the Servers node, then expand the GlassFish Server node.

Expand the Applications node.

Right-click the hello1 module and select Undeploy.

To delete the class files and other build artifacts, go back to the Projects tab, right-click the project, and select Clean.

6.3.5.2 To Undeploy the hello1 Web Module Using Maven

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/hello1/

Enter the following command:

mvn cargo:undeploy

To delete the class files and other build artifacts, enter the following command:

mvn clean

6.4 A Web Module That Uses Java Servlet Technology: The hello2 Example

The hello2 application is a web module that uses Java Servlet technology to display a greeting and response. You can use a text editor to view the application files, or you can use NetBeans IDE.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/servlet/hello2/ directory.

6.4.1 Mapping URLs to Web Components

When it receives a request, the web container must determine which web component should handle the request. The web container does so by mapping the URL path contained in the request to a web application and a web component. A URL path contains the context root and, optionally, a URL pattern:

http://host:port/context-root[/url-pattern]

You set the URL pattern for a servlet by using the @WebServlet annotation in the servlet source file. For example, the GreetingServlet.java file in the hello2 application contains the following annotation, specifying the URL pattern as /greeting:

@WebServlet("/greeting")
public class GreetingServlet extends HttpServlet {
    ...

This annotation indicates that the URL pattern /greeting follows the context root. Therefore, when the servlet is deployed locally, it is accessed with the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/hello2/greeting

To access the servlet by using only the context root, specify "/" as the URL pattern.

6.4.2 Examining the hello2 Web Module

The hello2 application behaves almost identically to the hello1 application, but it is implemented using Java Servlet technology instead of JavaServer Faces technology. You can use a text editor to view the application files, or you can use NetBeans IDE.

6.4.2.1 To View the hello2 Web Module Using NetBeans IDE

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/servlet

Select the hello2 folder and click Open Project.

Expand the Source Packages node, then expand the javaeetutorial.hello2 node.

Double-click the GreetingServlet.java file to view it.

This servlet overrides the doGet method, implementing the GET method of HTTP. The servlet displays a simple HTML greeting form whose Submit button, like that of hello1, specifies a response page for its action. The following excerpt begins with the @WebServlet annotation, which specifies the URL pattern relative to the context root:

@WebServlet("/greeting")
public class GreetingServlet extends HttpServlet {

    @Override
    public void doGet(HttpServletRequest request,
            HttpServletResponse response)
            throws ServletException, IOException {

        response.setContentType("text/html");
        response.setBufferSize(8192);
        try (PrintWriter out = response.getWriter()) {
            out.println("<html lang=\"en\">"
                    + "<head><title>Servlet Hello</title></head>");

            // then write the data of the response
            out.println("<body  bgcolor=\"#ffffff\">"
                + "<img src=\"duke.waving.gif\" "
                + "alt=\"Duke waving his hand\">"
                + "<form method=\"get\">"
                + "<h2>Hello, my name is Duke. What's yours?</h2>"
                + "<input title=\"My name is: \"type=\"text\" "
                + "name=\"username\" size=\"25\">"
                + "<p></p>"
                + "<input type=\"submit\" value=\"Submit\">"
                + "<input type=\"reset\" value=\"Reset\">"
                + "</form>");

            String username = request.getParameter("username");
            if (username != null && username.length()> 0) {
                RequestDispatcher dispatcher =
                    getServletContext().getRequestDispatcher("/response");

                if (dispatcher != null) {
                    dispatcher.include(request, response);
                }
            }
            out.println("</body></html>");
        }
    }
    ...

Double-click the ResponseServlet.java file to view it.

This servlet also overrides the doGet method, displaying only the response. The following excerpt begins with the @WebServlet annotation, which specifies the URL pattern relative to the context root:

@WebServlet("/response")
public class ResponseServlet extends HttpServlet {

    @Override
    public void doGet(HttpServletRequest request,
            HttpServletResponse response)
            throws ServletException, IOException {
        try (PrintWriter out = response.getWriter()) {

            // then write the data of the response
            String username = request.getParameter("username");
            if (username != null && username.length()> 0) {
                out.println("<h2>Hello, " + username + "!</h2>");
            }
        }
    }
    ...

6.4.3 Running the hello2 Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the hello2 example.

6.4.3.1 To Run the hello2 Example Using NetBeans IDE

Start GlassFish Server as described in To Start GlassFish Server Using NetBeans IDE, if you have not already done so.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/servlet

Select the hello2 folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the hello2 project and select Build to package and deploy the project.

In a web browser, open the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/hello2/greeting

The URL specifies the context root, followed by the URL pattern.

The application looks much like the hello1 application. The major difference is that after you click Submit the response appears below the greeting, not on a separate page.

6.4.3.2 To Run the hello2 Example Using Maven

Start GlassFish Server as described in To Start GlassFish Server Using the Command Line, if you have not already done so.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/servlet/hello2/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This target builds the WAR file, copies it to the tut-install/examples/web/hello2/target/ directory, and deploys it.

In a web browser, open the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/hello2/greeting

The URL specifies the context root, followed by the URL pattern.

The application looks much like the hello1 application. The major difference is that after you click Submit the response appears below the greeting, not on a separate page.

6.5 Configuring Web Applications

This section describes the following tasks involved with configuring web applications:

Setting context parameters

Declaring welcome files

Mapping errors to error screens

Declaring resource references

6.5.1 Setting Context Parameters

The web components in a web module share an object that represents their application context. You can pass context parameters to the context, or you can pass initialization parameters to a servlet. Context parameters are available to the entire application. For information on initialization parameters, see Creating and Initializing a Servlet.

6.5.1.1 To Add a Context Parameter Using NetBeans IDE

These steps apply generally to web applications but do not apply specifically to the examples in this chapter.

Open the project.

Expand the project's node in the Projects tree.

Expand the Web Pages node and then the WEB-INF node.

Double-click web.xml.

If the project does not have a web.xml file, create one by following the steps in To Create a web.xml File Using NetBeans IDE.

Click General at the top of the editor window.

Expand the Context Parameters node.

Click Add.

In the Add Context Parameter dialog box, in the Parameter Name field, enter the name that specifies the context object.

In the Parameter Value field, enter the parameter to pass to the context object.

Click OK.

6.5.1.2 To Create a web.xml File Using NetBeans IDE

From the File menu, choose New File.

In the New File wizard, select the Web category, then select Standard Deployment Descriptor under File Types.

Click Next.

Click Finish.

A basic web.xml file appears in web/WEB-INF/.

6.5.2 Declaring Welcome Files

The welcome files mechanism allows you to specify a list of files that the web container can append to a request for a URL (called a valid partial request) that is not mapped to a web component. For example, suppose that you define a welcome file welcome.html. When a client requests a URL such as host:port/webapp/directory, where directory is not mapped to a servlet or XHTML page, the file host:port/webapp/directory/welcome.html is returned to the client.

If a web container receives a valid partial request, the web container examines the welcome file list, appends to the partial request each welcome file in the order specified, and checks whether a static resource or servlet in the WAR is mapped to that request URL. The web container then sends the request to the first resource that matches in the WAR.

If no welcome file is specified, GlassFish Server will use a file named index.html as the default welcome file. If there is no welcome file and no file named index.html, GlassFish Server returns a directory listing.

You specify welcome files in the web.xml file. The welcome file specification for the hello1 example looks like this:

<welcome-file-list>
    <welcome-file>index.xhtml</welcome-file>
</welcome-file-list>

A specified welcome file must not have a leading or trailing slash (/).

The hello2 example does not specify a welcome file, because the URL request is mapped to the GreetingServlet web component through the URL pattern /greeting.

6.5.3 Mapping Errors to Error Screens

When an error occurs during execution of a web application, you can have the application display a specific error screen according to the type of error. In particular, you can specify a mapping between the status code returned in an HTTP response or a Java programming language exception returned by any web component and any type of error screen.

You can have multiple error-page elements in your deployment descriptor. Each element identifies a different error that causes an error page to open. This error page can be the same for any number of error-page elements.

6.5.3.1 To Set Up Error Mapping Using NetBeans IDE

These steps apply generally to web applications but do not apply specifically to the examples in this chapter.

Open the project.

Expand the project's node in the Projects tab.

Expand the Web Pages node and then the WEB-INF node.

Double-click web.xml.

If the project does not have a web.xml file, create one by following the steps in To Create a web.xml File Using NetBeans IDE.

Click Pages at the top of the editor window.

Expand the Error Pages node.

Click Add.

In the Add Error Page dialog box, click Browse to locate the page that you want to act as the error page.

Specify either an error code or an exception type.

To specify an error code, in the Error Code field enter the HTTP status code that will cause the error page to be opened, or leave the field blank to include all error codes.

To specify an exception type, in the Exception Type field enter the exception that will cause the error page to load. To specify all throwable errors and exceptions, enter java.lang.Throwable.

Click OK.

6.5.4 Declaring Resource References

If your web component uses such objects as enterprise beans, data sources, or web services, you use Java EE annotations to inject these resources into your application. Annotations eliminate a lot of the boilerplate lookup code and configuration elements that previous versions of Java EE required.

Although resource injection using annotations can be more convenient for the developer, there are some restrictions on using it in web applications. First, you can inject resources only into container-managed objects, because a container must have control over the creation of a component so that it can perform the injection into a component. As a result, you cannot inject resources into such objects as simple JavaBeans components. However, managed beans are managed by the container; therefore, they can accept resource injections.

Components that can accept resource injections are listed in Table 6-1.

This section explains how to use a couple of the annotations supported by a web container to inject resources. Chapter 38, "Running the Persistence Examples", explains how web applications use annotations supported by the Java Persistence API. Chapter 48, "Getting Started Securing Web Applications", explains how to use annotations to specify information about securing web applications. See Chapter 52, "Resource Adapters and Contracts", for more information on resources.

Table 6-1 Web Components That Accept Resource Injections

Component | Interface/Class

Servlets

|

javax.servlet.Servlet

Servlet filters

|

javax.servlet.ServletFilter

Event listeners

|

javax.servlet.ServletContextListener

javax.servlet.ServletContextAttributeListener

javax.servlet.ServletRequestListener

javax.servlet.ServletRequestAttributeListener

javax.servlet.http.HttpSessionListener

javax.servlet.http.HttpSessionAttributeListener

javax.servlet.http.HttpSessionBindingListener

Managed beans

|

Plain Old Java Objects

6.5.4.1 Declaring a Reference to a Resource

The @Resource annotation is used to declare a reference to a resource, such as a data source, an enterprise bean, or an environment entry.

The @Resource annotation is specified on a class, a method, or a field. The container is responsible for injecting references to resources declared by the @Resource annotation and mapping it to the proper JNDI resources.

In the following example, the @Resource annotation is used to inject a data source into a component that needs to make a connection to the data source, as is done when using JDBC technology to access a relational database:

@Resource javax.sql.DataSource catalogDS;
public getProductsByCategory() {
    // get a connection and execute the query
    Connection conn = catalogDS.getConnection();
    ...
}

The container injects this data source prior to the component's being made available to the application. The data source JNDI mapping is inferred from the field name, catalogDS, and the type, javax.sql.DataSource.

If you have multiple resources that you need to inject into one component, you need to use the @Resources annotation to contain them, as shown by the following example:

@Resources ({
    @Resource(name="myDB" type=javax.sql.DataSource.class),
    @Resource(name="myMQ" type=javax.jms.ConnectionFactory.class)
})

The web application examples in this tutorial use the Java Persistence API to access relational databases. This API does not require you to explicitly create a connection to a data source. Therefore, the examples do not use the @Resource annotation to inject a data source. However, this API supports the @PersistenceUnit and @PersistenceContext annotations for injecting EntityManagerFactory and EntityManager instances, respectively. Chapter 38, "Running the Persistence Examples" describes these annotations and the use of the Java Persistence API in web applications.

6.5.4.2 Declaring a Reference to a Web Service

The @WebServiceRef annotation provides a reference to a web service. The following example shows uses the @WebServiceRef annotation to declare a reference to a web service. WebServiceRef uses the wsdlLocation element to specify the URI of the deployed service's WSDL file:

...
import javax.xml.ws.WebServiceRef;
...
public class ResponseServlet extends HTTPServlet {
@WebServiceRef(wsdlLocation="http://localhost:8080/helloservice/hello?wsdl")
static HelloService service;

6.6 Further Information about Web Applications

For more information on web applications, see

JavaServer Faces 2.2 specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=344

Java Servlet 3.1 specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=340

18 Java API for WebSocket

This chapter describes the Java API for WebSocket (JSR 356), which provides support for creating WebSocket applications. WebSocket is an application protocol that provides full-duplex communications between two peers over the TCP protocol.

In the traditional request-response model used in HTTP, the client requests resources, and the server provides responses. The exchange is always initiated by the client; the server cannot send any data without the client requesting it first. This model worked well for the World Wide Web when clients made occasional requests for documents that changed infrequently, but the limitations of this approach are increasingly relevant as content changes quickly and users expect a more interactive experience on the Web. The WebSocket protocol addresses these limitations by providing a full-duplex communication channel between the client and the server. Combined with other client technologies, such as JavaScript and HTML5, WebSocket enables web applications to deliver a richer user experience.

The following topics are addressed here:

Introduction to WebSocket

Creating WebSocket Applications in the Java EE Platform

Programmatic Endpoints

Annotated Endpoints

Sending and Receiving Messages

Maintaining Client State

Using Encoders and Decoders

Path Parameters

Handling Errors

Specifying an Endpoint Configurator Class

The dukeetf2 Example Application

The websocketbot Example Application

Further Information about WebSocket

18.1 Introduction to WebSocket

In a WebSocket application, the server publishes a WebSocket endpoint, and the client uses the endpoint's URI to connect to the server. The WebSocket protocol is symmetrical after the connection has been established; the client and the server can send messages to each other at any time while the connection is open, and they can close the connection at any time. Clients usually connect only to one server, and servers accept connections from multiple clients.

The WebSocket protocol has two parts: handshake and data transfer. The client initiates the handshake by sending a request to a WebSocket endpoint using its URI. The handshake is compatible with existing HTTP-based infrastructure: web servers interpret it as an HTTP connection upgrade request. An example handshake from a client looks like this:

GET /path/to/websocket/endpoint HTTP/1.1
Host: localhost
Upgrade: websocket
Connection: Upgrade
Sec-WebSocket-Key: xqBt3ImNzJbYqRINxEFlkg==
Origin: http://localhost
Sec-WebSocket-Version: 13

An example handshake from the server in response to the client looks like this:

HTTP/1.1 101 Switching Protocols
Upgrade: websocket
Connection: Upgrade
Sec-WebSocket-Accept: K7DJLdLooIwIG/MOpvWFB3y3FE8=

The server applies a known operation to the value of the Sec-WebSocket-Key header to generate the value of the Sec-WebSocket-Accept header. The client applies the same operation to the value of the Sec-WebSocket-Key header, and the connection is established successfully if the result matches the value received from the server. The client and the server can send messages to each other after a successful handshake.

WebSocket supports text messages (encoded as UTF-8) and binary messages. The control frames in WebSocket are close, ping, and pong (a response to a ping frame). Ping and pong frames may also contain application data.

WebSocket endpoints are represented by URIs that have the following form:

ws://host:port/path?query
wss://host:port/path?query

The ws scheme represents an unencrypted WebSocket connection, and the wss scheme represents an encrypted connection. The port component is optional; the default port number is 80 for unencrypted connections and 443 for encrypted connections. The path component indicates the location of an endpoint within a server. The query component is optional.

Modern web browsers implement the WebSocket protocol and provide a JavaScript API to connect to endpoints, send messages, and assign callback methods for WebSocket events (such as opened connections, received messages, and closed connections).

18.2 Creating WebSocket Applications in the Java EE Platform

The Java EE platform includes the Java API for WebSocket (JSR 356), which enables you to create, configure, and deploy WebSocket endpoints in web applications. The WebSocket client API specified in JSR 356 also enables you to access remote WebSocket endpoints from any Java application.

The Java API for WebSocket consists of the following packages.

The javax.websocket.server package contains annotations, classes, and interfaces to create and configure server endpoints.

The javax.websocket package contains annotations, classes, interfaces, and exceptions that are common to client and server endpoints.

WebSocket endpoints are instances of the javax.websocket.Endpoint class. The Java API for WebSocket enables you to create two kinds of endpoints: programmatic endpoints and annotated endpoints. To create a programmatic endpoint, you extend the Endpoint class and override its lifecycle methods. To create an annotated endpoint, you decorate a Java class and some of its methods with the annotations provided by the packages mentioned previously. After you have created an endpoint, you deploy it to an specific URI in the application so that remote clients can connect to it.

Note:

In most cases, it is easier to create and deploy an annotated endpoint than a programmatic endpoint. This chapter provides a simple example of a programmatic endpoint, but it focuses on annotated endpoints.

The process for creating and deploying a WebSocket endpoint follows.

Create an endpoint class.

Implement the lifecycle methods of the endpoint.

Add your business logic to the endpoint.

Deploy the endpoint inside a web application.

The process is slightly different for programmatic endpoints and annotated endpoints, and it is covered in detail in the following sections.

Note:

As opposed to servlets, WebSocket endpoints are instantiated multiple times. The container creates an instance of an endpoint per connection to its deployment URI. Each instance is associated with one and only one connection. This facilitates keeping user state for each connection and makes development easier, because there is only one thread executing the code of an endpoint instance at any given time.

18.3 Programmatic Endpoints

The following example shows how to create an endpoint by extending the Endpoint class:

public class EchoEndpoint extends Endpoint {
   @Override
   public void onOpen(final Session session, EndpointConfig config) {
      session.addMessageHandler(new MessageHandler.Whole<String>() {
         @Override
         public void onMessage(String msg) {
            try {
               session.getBasicRemote().sendText(msg);
            } catch (IOException e) { ... }
         }
      });
   }
}

This endpoint echoes every message received. The Endpoint class defines three lifecycle methods: onOpen, onClose, and onError. The EchoEndpoint class implements the onOpen method, which is the only abstract method in the Endpoint class.

The Session parameter represents a conversation between this endpoint and the remote endpoint. The addMessageHandler method registers message handlers, and the getBasicRemote method returns an object that represents the remote endpoint. The Session interface is covered in detail in the rest of this chapter.

The message handler is implemented as an anonymous inner class. The onMessage method of the message handler is invoked when the endpoint receives a text message.

To deploy this programmatic endpoint, use the following code in your Java EE application:

ServerEndpointConfig.Builder.create(EchoEndpoint.class, "/echo").build();

When you deploy your application, the endpoint is available at ws://<host>:<port>/<application>/echo; for example, ws://localhost:8080/echoapp/echo.

18.4 Annotated Endpoints

The following example shows how to create the same endpoint from Programmatic Endpoints using annotations instead:

@ServerEndpoint("/echo")
public class EchoEndpoint {
   @OnMessage
   public void onMessage(Session session, String msg) {
      try {
         session.getBasicRemote().sendText(msg);
      } catch (IOException e) { ... }
   }
}

The annotated endpoint is simpler than the equivalent programmatic endpoint, and it is deployed automatically with the application to the relative path defined in the ServerEndpoint annotation. Instead of having to create an additional class for the message handler, this example uses the OnMessage annotation to designate the method invoked to handle messages.

Table 18-1 lists the annotations available in the javax.websocket package to designate the methods that handle lifecycle events. The examples in the table show the most common parameters for these methods. See the API reference for details on what combinations of parameters are allowed in each case.

Table 18-1 WebSocket Endpoint Lifecycle Annotations

Annotation | Event | Example

OnOpen

|

Connection opened

|

@OnOpen
public void open(Session session, 
                 EndpointConfig conf) { }

OnMessage

|

Message received

|

@OnMessage
public void message(Session session, 
                    String msg) { }

OnError

|

Connection error

|

@OnError
public void error(Session session, 
                  Throwable error) { }

OnClose

|

Connection closed

|

@OnClose
public void close(Session session, 
                  CloseReason reason) { }

18.5 Sending and Receiving Messages

WebSocket endpoints can send and receive text and binary messages. In addition, they can also send ping frames and receive pong frames. This section describes how to use the Session and RemoteEndpoint interfaces to send messages to the connected peer and how to use the OnMessage annotation to receive messages from it.

18.5.1 Sending Messages

Follow these steps to send messages in an endpoint.

Obtain the Session object from the connection.

The Session object is available as a parameter in the annotated lifecycle methods of the endpoint, like those in Table 18-1. When your message is a response to a message from the peer, you have the Session object available inside the method that received the message (the method annotated with @OnMessage). If you have to send messages that are not responses, store the Session object as an instance variable of the endpoint class in the method annotated with @OnOpen so that you can access it from other methods.

Use the Session object to obtain a RemoteEndpoint object.

The Session.getBasicRemote method and the Session.getAsyncRemote method return RemoteEndpoint.Basic and RemoteEndpoint.Async objects respectively. The RemoteEndpoint.Basic interface provides blocking methods to send messages; the RemoteEndpoint.Async interface provides nonblocking methods.

Use the RemoteEndpoint object to send messages to the peer.

The following list shows some of the methods you can use to send messages to the peer.

void RemoteEndpoint.Basic.sendText(String text)

Send a text message to the peer. This method blocks until the whole message has been transmitted.

void RemoteEndpoint.Basic.sendBinary(ByteBuffer data)

Send a binary message to the peer. This method blocks until the whole message has been transmitted.

void RemoteEndpoint.sendPing(ByteBuffer appData)

Send a ping frame to the peer.

void RemoteEndpoint.sendPong(ByteBuffer appData)

Send a pong frame to the peer.

The example in Annotated Endpoints demonstrates how to use this procedure to reply to every incoming text message.

18.5.1.1 Sending Messages to All Peers Connected to an Endpoint

Each instance of an endpoint class is associated with one and only one connection and peer; however, there are cases in which an endpoint instance needs to send messages to all connected peers. Examples include chat applications and online auctions. The Session interface provides the getOpenSessions method for this purpose. The following example demonstrates how to use this method to forward incoming text messages to all connected peers:

@ServerEndpoint("/echoall")
public class EchoAllEndpoint {
   @OnMessage
   public void onMessage(Session session, String msg) {
      try {
         for (Session sess : session.getOpenSessions()) {
            if (sess.isOpen())
               sess.getBasicRemote().sendText(msg);
         }
      } catch (IOException e) { ... }
   }
}

18.5.2 Receiving Messages

The OnMessage annotation designates methods that handle incoming messages. You can have at most three methods annotated with @OnMessage in an endpoint, one for each message type: text, binary, and pong. The following example demonstrates how to designate methods to receive all three types of messages:

@ServerEndpoint("/receive")
public class ReceiveEndpoint {
   @OnMessage
   public void textMessage(Session session, String msg) {
      System.out.println("Text message: " + msg);
   }
   @OnMessage
   public void binaryMessage(Session session, ByteBuffer msg) {
      System.out.println("Binary message: " + msg.toString());
   }
   @OnMessage
   public void pongMessage(Session session, PongMessage msg) {
      System.out.println("Pong message: " + 
                          msg.getApplicationData().toString());
   }
}

18.6 Maintaining Client State

Because the container creates an instance of the endpoint class for every connection, you can define and use instance variables to store client state information. In addition, the Session.getUserProperties method provides a modifiable map to store user properties. For example, the following endpoint replies to incoming text messages with the contents of the previous message from each client:

@ServerEndpoint("/delayedecho")
public class DelayedEchoEndpoint {
   @OnOpen
   public void open(Session session) {
      session.getUserProperties().put("previousMsg", " ");
   }
   @OnMessage
   public void message(Session session, String msg) {
      String prev = (String) session.getUserProperties()
                                    .get("previousMsg");
      session.getUserProperties().put("previousMsg", msg);
      try {
         session.getBasicRemote().sendText(prev);
      } catch (IOException e) { ... }
   }
}

To store information common to all connected clients, you can use class (static) variables; however, you are responsible for ensuring thread-safe access to them.

18.7 Using Encoders and Decoders

The Java API for WebSocket provides support for converting between WebSocket messages and custom Java types using encoders and decoders. An encoder takes a Java object and produces a representation that can be transmitted as a WebSocket message; for example, encoders typically produce JSON, XML, or binary representations. A decoder performs the reverse function; it reads a WebSocket message and creates a Java object.

This mechanism simplifies WebSocket applications, because it decouples the business logic from the serialization and deserialization of objects.

18.7.1 Implementing Encoders to Convert Java Objects into WebSocket Messages

The procedure to implement and use encoders in endpoints follows.

Implement one of the following interfaces:

Encoder.Text<T> for text messages

Encoder.Binary<T> for binary messages

These interfaces specify the encode method. Implement an encoder class for each custom Java type that you want to send as a WebSocket message.

Add the names of your encoder implementations to the encoders optional parameter of the ServerEndpoint annotation.

Use the sendObject(Object data) method of the RemoteEndpoint.Basic or RemoteEndpoint.Async interfaces to send your objects as messages. The container looks for an encoder that matches your type and uses it to convert the object to a WebSocket message.

For example, if you have two Java types (MessageA and MessageB) that you want to send as text messages, implement the Encoder.Text<MessageA> and Encoder.Text<MessageB> interfaces as follows:

public class MessageATextEncoder implements Encoder.Text<MessageA> {
   @Override
   public void init(EndpointConfig ec) { }
   @Override
   public void destroy() { }
   @Override
   public String encode(MessageA msgA) throws EncodeException {
      // Access msgA's properties and convert to JSON text...
      return msgAJsonString;
   }
}

Implement Encoder.Text<MessageB> similarly. Then, add the encoders parameter to the ServerEndpoint annotation as follows:

@ServerEndpoint(
   value = "/myendpoint",
   encoders = { MessageATextEncoder.class, MessageBTextEncoder.class }
)
public class EncEndpoint { ... }

Now, you can send MessageA and MessageB objects as WebSocket messages using the sendObject method as follows:

MessageA msgA = new MessageA(...);
MessageB msgB = new MessageB(...);
session.getBasicRemote.sendObject(msgA);
session.getBasicRemote.sendObject(msgB);

As in this example, you can have more than one encoder for text messages and more than one encoder for binary messages. Like endpoints, encoder instances are associated with one and only one WebSocket connection and peer, so there is only one thread executing the code of an encoder instance at any given time.

18.7.2 Implementing Decoders to Convert WebSocket Messages into Java Objects

The procedure to implement and use decoders in endpoints follows.

Implement one of the following interfaces:

Decoder.Text<T> for text messages

Decoder.Binary<T> for binary messages

These interfaces specify the willDecode and decode methods.

Note:

Unlike with encoders, you can specify at most one decoder for binary messages and one decoder for text messages.

Add the names of your decoder implementations to the decoders optional parameter of the ServerEndpoint annotation.

Use the OnMessage annotation in the endpoint to designate a method that takes your custom Java type as a parameter. When the endpoint receives a message that can be decoded by one of the decoders you specified, the container calls the method annotated with @OnMessage that takes your custom Java type as a parameter if this method exists.

For example, if you have two Java types (MessageA and MessageB) that you want to send and receive as text messages, define them so that they extend a common class (Message). Because you can only define one decoder for text messages, implement a decoder for the Message class as follows:

public class MessageTextDecoder implements Decoder.Text<Message> {
   @Override
   public void init(EndpointConfig ec) { }
   @Override
   public void destroy() { }
   @Override
   public Message decode(String string) throws DecodeException {
      // Read message...
      if ( /* message is an A message */ )
         return new MessageA(...);
      else if ( /* message is a B message */ )
         return new MessageB(...);
   }
   @Override
   public boolean willDecode(String string) {
      // Determine if the message can be converted into either a
      // MessageA object or a MessageB object...
      return canDecode;
   }
}

Then, add the decoder parameter to the ServerEndpoint annotation as follows:

@ServerEndpoint(
   value = "/myendpoint",
   encoders = { MessageATextEncoder.class, MessageBTextEncoder.class },
   decoders = { MessageTextDecoder.class }
)
public class EncDecEndpoint { ... }

Now, define a method in the endpoint class that receives MessageA and MessageB objects as follows:

@OnMessage
public void message(Session session, Message msg) {
   if (msg instanceof MessageA) {
      // We received a MessageA object...
   } else if (msg instanceof MessageB) {
      // We received a MessageB object...
   }
}

Like endpoints, decoder instances are associated with one and only one WebSocket connection and peer, so there is only one thread executing the code of a decoder instance at any given time.

18.8 Path Parameters

The ServerEndpoint annotation enables you to use URI templates to specify parts of an endpoint deployment URI as application parameters. For example, consider this endpoint:

@ServerEndpoint("/chatrooms/{room-name}")
public class ChatEndpoint {
   ...
}

If the endpoint is deployed inside a web application called chatapp at a local Java EE server in port 8080, clients can connect to the endpoint using any of the following URIs:

http://localhost:8080/chatapp/chatrooms/currentnews
http://localhost:8080/chatapp/chatrooms/music
http://localhost:8080/chatapp/chatrooms/cars
http://localhost:8080/chatapp/chatrooms/technology

Annotated endpoints can receive path parameters as arguments in methods annotated with @OnOpen, @OnMessage, and @OnClose. In this example, the endpoint uses the parameter in the @OnOpen method to determine which chat room the client wants to join:

@ServerEndpoint("/chatrooms/{room-name}")
public class ChatEndpoint {
   @OnOpen
   public void open(Session session, 
                    EndpointConfig c, 
                    @PathParam("room-name") String roomName) {
      // Add the client to the chat room of their choice ...
   }
}

The path parameters used as arguments in these methods can be strings, primitive types, or the corresponding wrapper types.

18.9 Handling Errors

To designate a method that handles errors in an annotated WebSocket endpoint, decorate it with @OnError:

@ServerEndpoint("/testendpoint")
public class TestEndpoint {
   ...
   @OnError
   public void error(Session session, Throwable t) {
      t.printStackTrace();
      ...
   }
}

This method is invoked when there are connection problems, runtime errors from message handlers, or conversion errors when decoding messages.

18.10 Specifying an Endpoint Configurator Class

The Java API for WebSocket enables you to configure how the container creates server endpoint instances. You can provide custom endpoint configuration logic to:

Access the details of the initial HTTP request for a WebSocket connection

Perform custom checks on the Origin HTTP header

Modify the WebSocket handshake response

Choose a WebSocket subprotocol from those requested by the client

Control the instantiation and initialization of endpoint instances

To provide custom endpoint configuration logic, you extend the ServerEndpointConfig.Configurator class and override some of its methods. In the endpoint class, you specify the configurator class using the configurator parameter of the ServerEndpoint annotation.

For example, the following configurator class makes the handshake request object available to endpoint instances:

public class CustomConfigurator extends ServerEndpointConfig.Configurator {

    @Override
    public void modifyHandshake(ServerEndpointConfig conf,
                                HandshakeRequest req,
                                HandshakeResponse resp) {

        conf.getUserProperties().put("handshakereq", req);
    }

}

The following endpoint class configures endpoint instances with the custom configurator, which enables them to access the handshake request object:

@ServerEndpoint(
    value = "/myendpoint",
    configurator = CustomConfigurator.class
)
public class MyEndpoint {

    @OnOpen
    public void open(Session s, EndpointConfig conf) {
        HandshakeRequest req = (HandshakeRequest) conf.getUserProperties()
                                                      .get("handshakereq");
        Map<String,List<String>> headers = req.getHeaders();
        ...
    }
}

The endpoint class can use the handshake request object to access the details of the initial HTTP request, such as its headers or the HttpSession object.

For more information on endpoint configuration, see the API reference for the ServerEndpointConfig.Configurator class.

18.11 The dukeetf2 Example Application

The dukeetf2 example application, located in the tut-install/examples/web/websocket/dukeetf2/ directory, demonstrates how to use a WebSocket endpoint to provide data updates to web clients. The example resembles a service that provides periodic updates on the price and trading volume of an electronically traded fund (ETF).

18.11.1 Architecture of the dukeetf2 Sample Application

The dukeetf2 example application consists of a WebSocket endpoint, an enterprise bean, and an HTML page.

The endpoint accepts connections from clients and sends them updates when new data for price and trading volume becomes available.

The enterprise bean updates the price and volume information once every second.

The HTML page uses JavaScript code to connect to the WebSocket endpoint, parse incoming messages, and update the price and volume information without reloading the page.

18.11.1.1 The Endpoint

The WebSocket endpoint is implemented in the ETFEndpoint class, which stores all connected sessions in a queue and provides a method that the enterprise bean calls when there is new information available to send:

@ServerEndpoint("/dukeetf")
public class ETFEndpoint {
   private static final Logger logger = Logger.getLogger("ETFEndpoint");
   /* Queue for all open WebSocket sessions */
   static Queue<Session> queue = new ConcurrentLinkedQueue<>();

   /* PriceVolumeBean calls this method to send updates */
   public static void send(double price, int volume) {
      String msg = String.format("%.2f / %d", price, volume);
      try {
         /* Send updates to all open WebSocket sessions */
         for (Session session : queue) {
            session.getBasicRemote().sendText(msg);
            logger.log(Level.INFO, "Sent: {0}", msg);
         }
      } catch (IOException e) {
         logger.log(Level.INFO, e.toString());
      }
    }
    ...
}

The lifecycle methods of the endpoint add and remove sessions to and from the queue:

@ServerEndpoint("/dukeetf")
public class ETFEndpoint {
   ...
   @OnOpen
   public void openConnection(Session session) {
      /* Register this connection in the queue */
      queue.add(session);
      logger.log(Level.INFO, "Connection opened.");
   }

   @OnClose
   public void closedConnection(Session session) {
      /* Remove this connection from the queue */
      queue.remove(session);
      logger.log(Level.INFO, "Connection closed.");
   }

   @OnError
   public void error(Session session, Throwable t) {
      /* Remove this connection from the queue */
      queue.remove(session);
      logger.log(Level.INFO, t.toString());
      logger.log(Level.INFO, "Connection error.");
   }
}

18.11.1.2 The Enterprise Bean

The enterprise bean uses the timer service to generate new price and volume information every second:

@Startup
@Singleton
public class PriceVolumeBean {
   /* Use the container's timer service */
   @Resource TimerService tservice;
   private Random random;
   private volatile double price = 100.0;
   private volatile int volume = 300000;
   private static final Logger logger = Logger.getLogger("PriceVolumeBean");
   
   @PostConstruct
   public void init() {
       /* Initialize the EJB and create a timer */
       logger.log(Level.INFO, "Initializing EJB.");
       random = new Random();
       tservice.createIntervalTimer(1000, 1000, new TimerConfig());
   }
   
   @Timeout
   public void timeout() {
       /* Adjust price and volume and send updates */
       price += 1.0*(random.nextInt(100)-50)/100.0;
       volume += random.nextInt(5000) - 2500;
       ETFEndpoint.send(price, volume);
   }
}

The enterprise bean calls the send method of the ETFEndpoint class in the timeout method. See Using the Timer Service in Chapter 34, "Running the Enterprise Bean Examples" for more information on the timer service.

18.11.1.3 The HTML Page

The HTML page consists of a table and some JavaScript code. The table contains two fields referenced from JavaScript code:

<!DOCTYPE html>
<html>
<head>...</head>
<body>
  ...
  <table>
    ...
    <td id="price">--.--</td>
    ...
    <td id="volume">--</td>
    ...
  </table>
</body>
</html>

The JavaScript code uses the WebSocket API to connect to the server endpoint and to designate a callback method for incoming messages. The callback method updates the page with the new information.

var wsocket;
function connect() {
   wsocket = new WebSocket("ws://localhost:8080/dukeetf2/dukeetf");
   wsocket.onmessage = onMessage;
}
function onMessage(evt) {
   var arraypv = evt.data.split("/");
   document.getElementById("price").innerHTML = arraypv[0];
   document.getElementById("volume").innerHTML = arraypv[1];
}
window.addEventListener("load", connect, false);

The WebSocket API is supported by most modern browsers, and it is widely used in HTML5 web client development.

18.11.2 Running the dukeetf2 Example Application

This section describes how to run the dukeetf2 example application using NetBeans IDE and from the command line.

18.11.2.1 To Run the dukeetf2 Example Application Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/websocket

Select the dukeetf2 folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the dukeetf2 project and select Run.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file (dukeetf2.war) located in the target/ directory, deploys it to the server, and launches a web browser window with the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/dukeetf2/

Open the same URL on a different web browser tab or window to see how both pages get price and volume updates simultaneously.

18.11.2.2 To Run the dukeetf2 Example Application Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/websocket/dukeetf2/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

Open a web browser window and enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/dukeetf2/

Open the same URL on a different web browser tab or window to see how both pages get price and volume updates simultaneously.

18.12 The websocketbot Example Application

The websocketbot example application, located in the tut-install/examples/web/websocket/websocketbot/ directory, demonstrates how to use a WebSocket endpoint to implement a chat. The example resembles a chat room in which many users can join and have a conversation. Users can ask simple questions to a bot agent that is always available in the chat room.

18.12.1 Architecture of the websocketbot Example Application

The websocketbot example application consists of the following elements:

A CDI bean (BotBean) that contains the logic for the bot agent to reply to messages

A WebSocket endpoint (BotEndpoint) that implements the chat room

A set of classes (Message, ChatMessage, InfoMessage, JoinMessage, and UsersMessage) that represent application messages

A set of classes (ChatMessageEncoder, InfoMessageEncoder, JoinMessageEncoder, and UsersMessageEncoder) that encode application messages into WebSocket text messages as JSON data

A class (MessageDecoder) the parses WebSocket text messages as JSON data and decodes them into JoinMessage or ChatMessage objects

An HTML page (index.html) that uses JavaScript code to implement the client for the chat room

18.12.1.1 The CDI Bean

The CDI bean (BotBean) is a Java class that contains the respond method. This method compares the incoming chat message with a set of predefined questions and returns a chat response.

@Named
public class BotBean {
    public String respond(String msg) { ... }
}

18.12.1.2 The WebSocket Endpoint

The WebSocket endpoint (BotEndpoint) is an annotated endpoint that performs the following functions:

Receives messages from clients

Forwards messages to clients

Maintains a list of connected clients

Invokes the bot agent functionality

The endpoint specifies its deployment URI and the message encoders and decoders using the ServerEndpoint annotation. The endpoint obtains an instance of the BotBean class and a managed executor service resource through dependency injection:

@ServerEndpoint(
   value = "/websocketbot",
   decoders = { MessageDecoder.class }, 
   encoders = { JoinMessageEncoder.class, ChatMessageEncoder.class, 
                InfoMessageEncoder.class, UsersMessageEncoder.class }
)
/* There is a BotEndpoint instance per connection */
public class BotEndpoint {
   private static final Logger logger = Logger.getLogger("BotEndpoint");
   /* Bot functionality bean */
   @Inject private BotBean botbean;
   /* Executor service for asynchronous processing */
   @Resource(name="comp/DefaultManagedExecutorService")
   private ManagedExecutorService mes;
   
   @OnOpen
   public void openConnection(Session session) {
       logger.log(Level.INFO, "Connection opened.");
   }
   ...
}

The message method processes incoming messages from clients. The decoder converts incoming text messages into JoinMessage or ChatMessage objects, which inherit from the Message class. The message method receives a Message object as a parameter:

@OnMessage
public void message(Session session, Message msg) {
   logger.log(Level.INFO, "Received: {0}", msg.toString());
   
   if (msg instanceof JoinMessage) {
      /* Add the new user and notify everybody */
      JoinMessage jmsg = (JoinMessage) msg;
      session.getUserProperties().put("name", jmsg.getName());
      session.getUserProperties().put("active", true);
      logger.log(Level.INFO, "Received: {0}", jmsg.toString());
      sendAll(session, new InfoMessage(jmsg.getName() + 
              " has joined the chat"));
      sendAll(session, new ChatMessage("Duke", jmsg.getName(), 
              "Hi there!!"));
      sendAll(session, new UsersMessage(this.getUserList(session)));
      
   } else if (msg instanceof ChatMessage) {
      /* Forward the message to everybody */
      ChatMessage cmsg = (ChatMessage) msg;
      logger.log(Level.INFO, "Received: {0}", cmsg.toString());
      sendAll(session, cmsg);
      if (cmsg.getTarget().compareTo("Duke") == 0) {
         /* The bot replies to the message */
         mes.submit(new Runnable() {
            @Override
            public void run() {
               String resp = botbean.respond(cmsg.getMessage());
               sendAll(session, new ChatMessage("Duke",
                       cmsg.getName(), resp));
            }
         });
      }
   }
}

If the message is a join message, the endpoint adds the new user to the list and notifies all connected clients. If the message is a chat message, the endpoint forwards it to all connected clients.

If a chat message is for the bot agent, the endpoint obtains a response using the BotBean instance and sends it to all connected clients. The sendAll method is similar to the example in Sending Messages to All Peers Connected to an Endpoint.

Asynchronous Processing and Concurrency Considerations

The WebSocket endpoint calls the BotBean.respond method to obtain a response from the bot. In this example, this is a blocking operation; the user that sent the associated message would not be able to send or receive other chat messages until the operation completes. To avoid this problem, the endpoint obtains an executor service from the container and executes the blocking operation in a different thread using the ManagedExecutorService.submit method from Concurrency Utilities for Java EE.

The Java API for WebSocket specification requires that Java EE implementations instantiate endpoint classes once per connection. This facilitates the development of WebSocket endpoints, because you are guaranteed that only one thread is executing the code in a WebSocket endpoint class at any given time. When you introduce a new thread in an endpoint, as in this example, you must ensure that variables and methods accessed by more than one thread are thread safe. In this example, the code in BotBean is thread safe, and the BotEndpoint.sendAll method has been declared synchronized.

Refer to Chapter 56, "Concurrency Utilities for Java EE" for more information on the managed executor service and Concurrency Utilities for Java EE.

18.12.1.3 The Application Messages

The classes that represent application messages (Message, ChatMessage, InfoMessage, JoinMessage, and UsersMessage) contain only properties and getter and setter methods. For example, the ChatMessage class looks like this:

public class ChatMessage extends Message {
    private String name;
    private String target;
    private String message;
    /* ... Constructor, getters, and setters ... */
}

18.12.1.4 The Encoder Classes

The encoder classes convert application message objects into JSON text using the Java API for JSON Processing. For example, the ChatMessageEncoder class is implemented as follows:

/* Encode a ChatMessage as JSON.
 * For example, (new ChatMessage("Peter","Duke","How are you?"))
 * is encoded as follows:
 * {"type":"chat","target":"Duke","message":"How are you?"}
 */
public class ChatMessageEncoder implements Encoder.Text<ChatMessage> {
   @Override
   public void init(EndpointConfig ec) { }
   @Override
   public void destroy() { }
   @Override
   public String encode(ChatMessage chatMessage) throws EncodeException {
      // Access properties in chatMessage and write JSON text...
   }
}

See Chapter 19, JSON Processing for more information on the Java API for JSON Processing.

18.12.1.5 The Message Decoder

The message decoder (MessageDecoder) class converts WebSocket text messages into application messages by parsing JSON text. It is implemented as follows:

/* Decode a JSON message into a JoinMessage or a ChatMessage.
 * For example, the incoming message
 * {"type":"chat","name":"Peter","target":"Duke","message":"How are you?"}
 * is decoded as (new ChatMessage("Peter", "Duke", "How are you?"))
 */
public class MessageDecoder implements Decoder.Text<Message> {
    /* Stores the name-value pairs from a JSON message as a Map */
    private Map<String,String> messageMap;

    @Override
    public void init(EndpointConfig ec) { }
    @Override
    public void destroy() { }

    /* Create a new Message object if the message can be decoded */
    @Override
    public Message decode(String string) throws DecodeException {
       Message msg = null;
       if (willDecode(string)) {
          switch (messageMap.get("type")) {
             case "join":
                msg = new JoinMessage(messageMap.get("name"));
                break;
             case "chat":
                msg = new ChatMessage(messageMap.get("name"),
                                      messageMap.get("target"),
                                      messageMap.get("message"));
          }
       } else {
          throw new DecodeException(string, "[Message] Can't decode.");
       }
       return msg;
   }
   
   /* Decode a JSON message into a Map and check if it contains
    * all the required fields according to its type. */
   @Override
   public boolean willDecode(String string) {
      // Convert JSON data from the message into a name-value map...
      // Check if the message has all the fields for its message type...
   }
}

18.12.1.6 The HTML Page

The HTML page (index.html) contains a field for the user name. After the user types a name and clicks Join, three text areas are available: one to type and send messages, one for the chat room, and one with the list of users. The page also contains a WebSocket console that shows the messages sent and received as JSON text.

The JavaScript code on the page uses the WebSocket API to connect to the endpoint, send messages, and designate callback methods. The WebSocket API is supported by most modern browsers and is widely used for web client development with HTML5.

18.12.2 Running the websocketbot Example Application

This section describes how to run the websocketbot example application using NetBeans IDE and from the command line.

18.12.2.1 To Run the websocketbot Example Application Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/websocket

Select the websocketbot folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the websocketbot project and select Run.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, websocketbot.war, located in the target/ directory; deploys it to the server; and launches a web browser window with the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/websocketbot/

See To Test the websocketbot Example Application for more information.

18.12.2.2 To Run the websocketbot Example Application Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/websocket/websocketbot/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

Open a web browser window and type the following address:

http://localhost:8080/websocketbot/

See To Test the websocketbot Example Application for more information.

18.12.2.3 To Test the websocketbot Example Application

On the main page, type your name on the first text field and press the Enter key.

The list of connected users appears on the text area on the right. The text area on the left is the chat room.

Type a message on the text area below the login button. For example, type the messages in bold and press enter to obtain responses similar to the following:

[--Peter has joined the chat--]
Duke: @Peter Hi there!!
Peter: @Duke how are you?
Duke: @Peter I'm doing great, thank you!
Peter: @Duke when is your birthday?
Duke: @Peter My birthday is on May 23rd. Thanks for asking!

Join the chat from another browser window by copying and pasting the URI on the address bar and joining with a different name.

The new user name appears in the list of users in both browser windows. You can send messages from either window and see how they appear in the other.

Click Show WebSocket Console.

The console shows the messages sent and received as JSON text.

18.13 Further Information about WebSocket

For more information on WebSocket in Java EE, see the Java API for WebSocket specification:

http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=356